Guide to the Eugene I. Rabinowitch Papers
University of Chicago Library
- Series I: Pugwash Conference Materials
  - Subseries 18: Twentieth Pugwash Conference, Fontana (Lake Geneva) Wisconsin
    - 20th Pugwash Conference, [Conference Reports] (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 20th Pugwash Conference, [Conference Reports] (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
    - 20th Pugwash Conference, [Conference Papers] (Box 10, Folder 6-8)
    - 20th Pugwash Conference, [ER's speech at the Conference] (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - 20th Pugwash Conference, Press clippings (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 19: Twenty-first Pugwash Conference, Sinaia, Romania
    - 21st Pugwash Conference, Sinaia, Romania, August 26-31, 1971, "Problems of World Security, Environment and Development" [Speeches and Papers] (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 21st Pugwash Conference, [Conference Papers] (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
    - 21st Pugwash Conference, [Conference Papers] (Box 11, Folder 4-8)
  - Subseries 20: Pugwash Symposiums, 1969-1971
    - 5th Pugwash Symposium, Marianske Lazne, Czechoslovakia, May 19-24, 1969 [Agenda] (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - 5th Pugwash Symposium, [Reports] (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - 5th Pugwash Symposium, [Reports] (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development, Stanford University, September 1-4, 1970 [Participants and proposed agenda] (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development, [Invitations; Asia] (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development, [Invitations; South America] (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development, [Invitations; Europe] (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development, [Invitations; U.S.A.] (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development, [Invitations; Africa] (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development, [Responses of Invitations] (Box 12, Folder 9-15)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development, [Agenda] (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development, [Financial and organizational statements and correspondence] (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development, [Financial and organizational statements and correspondence] (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development, Stanford University, September 1-4, 1970 [Papers sent to the Symposium] (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development. Stanford University, September 1-4, 1970 [Background papers] (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Pugwash Symposium on Science and Development. Stanford University, [Plans for publication of the proceedings] (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - 13th Pugwash Symposium, Frascati, Italy, April 14-17, 1971, "Social Aspects of Technological Change" (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 21: Articles, Documents, Correspondence, and Finances Related to Pugwash
    - Pugwash Study Group on Development (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Disarmament studies; Miscellaneous documents ca. 1968 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Disarmament; Proposed publication on (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - "Pugwash," article for Retort by ER (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - "The Pugwash Movement," article published in the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists, February, 1965 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Proposed Pugwash Journal (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Pugwash finances, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, Continuing Committee materials, documents relating to various conferences and symposia, etc. (Box 14, Folder 8-13)
    - General Correspondence, Continuing Committee materials, documents relating to various conferences and symposia, etc. (Box 15, Folder 1-11)
    - General Correspondence, Continuing Committee materials, documents relating to various conferences and symposia, etc. (Box 16, Folder 1-4)
    - Pugwash Newsletter, December 1959 (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Series II: Professional and Academic Materials
  - Subseries 1: Academic Papers
    - "Biophysics 301, Lectures, Fall 1961" (Box 16, Folder 6-7)
    - Resume on E. Rabinowitch written October 23, 1959 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2: Documents on science in the Soviet Union
    - Soviet research laboratories; mimeographed lists (Box 16, Folder 9-10)
    - Conditions of Research in Soviet Biology (in Russian), mimeograph (Box 16, Folder 11-12)
    - Human Science-Neither West nor East, mimeographed copy (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Research Program on the U.S.S.R.; direct mail advertisements, publishers' price lists, enclosed complimentary paper; lists of Soviet publications (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Soviet science; miscellaneous clippings, speeches, letters between Katherine Lonsdale and E. Rabinowitch concerning her Russian trip (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Letters from academicians Topchiev and DS to E. Rabinowitch, draft of Bulletin article on the letters, press releases on the letters; miscellaneous clippings and mimeographed statements on the Soviet reaction to Pugwash; copies of Pravda, Izvestia and New Time (Box 16, Folder 16-18)
  - Subseries 3: Notes for speeches and talks
    - Folder1: Conference Scientifique sur les Dangers Atomique; E. Rabinowitch's Conference notes and notes for a speech (Box 17)
    - Speeches, announcements and notes (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Speeches, Madison, February 28-March 1, 1961; Kalamazoo College, March 16, 1961; St. Louis, May 8, 1961; Penn State, November 9, 1961 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Speeches, Madison, February 28-March 1, 1961; Unitarian students meeting, November 19, 1961; Bloomington, November 28, 1961; "Challenge," Ann Arbor, December 1, 1961; and undated speeches (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Speeches, Pugwash Participants meeting, New York City, November 23, 1958; speeches, miscellaneous and undated, but evidently written by E. Rabinowitch (Box 17, Folder 5-6)
  - Subseries 4: Clippings on science, politics and nuclear weapons
    - Civil defense; United States, Sweden (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Edward Condon-Disarmament (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Cyrus Eaton-German science (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Government and science; scientific legislation (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - History of science and the scientific method (Box 17, Folder 11-12)
    - Katz-Nuclear weapons and nuclear war (Box 17, Folder 13-14)
    - Physics-politics (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - The President and foreign policy-Publication (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Rabinowitch-Stevenson (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Technology (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Teller-Underdeveloped nations (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - United Nations University-Uranium (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Winter-World Health Organization (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Notes for Metallurgical Laboratory statement, August 7, 1945. Holograph (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Rabinowitch draft of Metallurgical Laboratory statement. Holograph and ditto with holograph corrections (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Metallurgical Laboratory statement, Part I Atomic Bomb and the Responsibility of Science Part II Analysis of the Situation Created by the Advent of Atomic Weapons. Part III International Controls, World Government and "Union Now." Holograph and ditto (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Memorandum from Jerome Fisher to E. Rabinowtich, January 22, 1946. Typescript, D. Jerome Fisher, University of Chicago, Aerial Survey as an Atomic Bomb Raw Material Control. Typescript carbon Information on ores. Holograph notes (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - National Aspects, revised 12-17-45. Used for Congressional Book. Typescript, International Aspects, revised 12-17-45. Used for Congressional Book. Rabinowitch. Typescript (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Domestic Legislation on Atomic Energy. Rabinowitch. 12-17-45. Typescript with holograph corrections, International Implications of Domestic Legislation. March 1946. Washington Speech Draft for Senate. Typescript carbon (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Rabinowitch, Preliminary Outline for Classified Study Concerning the Feasibility of Inspection of the World Plants for Concentrating Uranium-235 by Gaseous Diffusion. Two versions, the second dated January 15, 1946 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Reprints from the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists, January 1965 "New Year's Thoughts 1965" by E. Rabinowitch September 1965 "Pugwash XIV" November 1965 "The New Perspective" by E. Rabinowitch January 1966 "New Year's Thoughts 1966" by E. Rabinowitch (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 5: Correspondence with individuals
    - Appelman-Bohr (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Born-Bowles (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Brennan-Daniels (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - DuBridge-Einstein (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Feld-Goldsmith (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Gregory-Jaspers (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - Kemble-MacMahon (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - Magat-Pihl (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - Draft of letter to Bishop Oxman, 1946. Holograph (Box 18, Folder 20)
    - Revelle-Rotblat (Box 18, Folder 21)
    - Safford-Schelling (Box 18, Folder 22)
    - Schwarcz-Spingarn (Box 18, Folder 23)
    - Smythe (Box 18, Folder 24)
    - Staley-Swartz (Box 18, Folder 25)
    - Szilard (Box 18, Folder 26)
    - Teller-von Weizsacker (Box 18, Folder 27)
    - Watson-Wolfe, and unidentified letters (Box 18, Folder 28)
  - Subseries 6: E. Rabinowitch's correspondence with institutions and foundations
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences-American Veterans Committee (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Associated Universities; East River Project, Parts I, Ib, V (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Association d'Étude Pour l'Expansion de la Recherche Scientifique-Book publishing (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Brookings Institution; Arlie House Conference on Communications and Public Policy, December 15-17, 1961 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists; financial correspondence (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists ;fund raising, relations with foundations (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists; editorial policy, clippings, appraisals, proposals (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists ;miscellaneous proposals for articles (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists; mimeographed article from Le Figaro on Soviet atom plant; typed and handwritten drafts of article for the Bulletin by R. E. Lapp (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Article Proofs for Atomics, "Strategy and Disarmament" and an untitled article by Hans A. Bethe (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Bulletin Editorial Board; internal correspondence, agendas of meetings of Editorial Board and Board of Directors (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Bulletin Editorial Board; agendas and financial statements (bound copies) (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Carnegie Endowment Fund (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - Carnegie Endowment Fund Conference on Problems of War and Peace in the Atomic Age (bound volume) (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Challenge-Committee for World Development (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Committees of Correspondence, Champaign-Urbana Committee, readings no. 2 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Committees of Correspondence, bound readings (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Committees of Correspondence, newsletters (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Committees of Correspondence, Champaign-Urbana, Lake of the Woods Conference, statements and Conference notes in ER's hand; miscellaneous mimeographed statements disseminated by the Champaign-Urbana committee (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Committees of Correspondence (Chicago chapter?), mimeographed Bulletins (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Committees of Correspondence, National Head-quarters, minutes of Cambridge meeting, notes on Bear Mountain Conference, list of sponsors, statement of the National Committee, newsletters (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Committees of Correspondence, newsletters (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Congress for Cultural Freedom; correspondence with ER and mimeographed newsletters (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - "Science et Parti en U.R.S.S." March-June, 1954 and Science et Liberté No. 37, March 1954 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Congress International de Botanique (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Cornell University Professors; "A New Approach to Communicating with the Russians" and "The Mirror Image in Soviet-American Relations" (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - Council Against Communist Agression-Council for a Livable World (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Federation of American Scientists; "Problems of the Nuclear Arms Race" (bound folder), correspondence, mimeographed news release (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Guggenheim Foundation, "Heart Open to the World" (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - House of Representatives. New Civil Defense Program, 9th Report by the Committee on Government Operations, September 21, 1961 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Institute for International Order; Disarmament Studies Project, prospectus by Spingarn, correspondence and Institute Bulletin, paper by Lauritsen (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Institute for International Order; Gould House Conference on Science, lists of discussion topics, guests, programs, schedules, notes in ER's hand (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Institute for International Order; Gould House Conference, panel reports (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - International Commission for Ecology, International Review Service, mimeographed reviews of international affairs (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Liberal Congressmen; correspondence between ER and Representative Kastenmeier, thermofax copy of (ER's?) essay for the "Liberal Syllabus" (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Liberal Congressmen; Correspondence between ER and Marcus Raskin, staff report "Theory and Practice of Deterrence" by Raskin and Arthur Waskow (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Liberal Congressmen; "A New Liberalism in the Democratic Party" (mimeographed) (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Liberal Congressmen; copy of Congressional testimony; "A Re-examination of U.S. Foreign Policy" (draft of paper) (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - MIT Centennial Conference; correspondence, brochures, agendas (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - Mohawk Association of Scientists and Engineers; proposals on disarmament, mimeographed Bulletins; FAS Stand on Test Ban, mimeographed Bulletins; MASE Newsletter and miscellaneous mimeographed announcements (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - New World Foundation-Radiotelevisione Italiana (Box 21, Folder 15)
    - RIAS (University-of-the-Air, Berlin); correspondence to arrange lecture by ER (Box 21, Folder 16)
    - "Schreiber case"; correspondence, mimeographed memoranda (Box 21, Folder 17)
    - Science and Freedom Conference, Study Group (Paris, 1956); agendas, lists of participants, Conference notes in ER's hand (Box 21, Folder 18)
    - Science and Freedom Conference (Paris, 1956); Papers by Del Mazo-Hofer (Box 21, Folder 19)
    - Science and Freedom Conference (Paris, 1956); Papers; Perroux-Rabinowitch (Box 21, Folder 20)
    - Science and Freedom Conference (Paris, 1956); Papers; Sanchez-von Rauch (Box 21, Folder 21)
    - Science and Freedom Conference (Paris, 1956); miscellaneous Bulletins, extracts from letters, reports, etc. (Box 21, Folder 22)
    - Science and Freedom Committee; copies of A Bulletin of the Committee on Science and Freedom (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Science and Freedom Committee; Second Conference (1955), correspondence among ER, Edward Shills, and George Polanyi; typed and mimeographed proposals and memoranda, list of participants (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Science and Freedom; Second Conference (1955), papers by Clark and Wiles (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Science and Freedom; Second Conference (1955), miscellaneous Conference papers (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Scientists Committee for Radiation Information-Society for Visiting Scientists (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Stanford Research Institute; staff papers on underdeveloped countries (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Universal Calendar Society; mimeographed papers and reprints (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - World Academy of Arts and Sciences; typed "Manifesto," "Statutes;" mimeographed progress report (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - World Association of Parliamentarians for World Government, Conference of Scientists (London, 1955); brochures, programs, lists of participants, issue of World (Summer, 1955) (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - World Association of Parliamentarians for World Government, Conference of Scientists (London, 1955); correspondence with ER, Conference notes in ER's hand (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - World Association of Parliamentarians for World Government, Conference of Scientists (London, 1955); (ER's?) draft of an article on the Conference for the Bulletin (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - World Association of Parliamentarians for World Government, Conference of Scientists (London, 1955); resolutions, reports of commissions (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - World Association of Parliamentarians for World Government, Conference of Scientists (London, 1955); Conference papers by Boschi-Mariani (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - World Association of Parliamentarians for World Government, Conference of Scientists (London, 1955); Conference papers by de Schlippe-Topchiev (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - World Brotherhood; correspondence between Paul Hoffman and ER; bound working papers (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - World Conference Against A- and H-Bombs-World Constitutional Convention (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 7: Biographical materials
    - Drawing of Eugene Rabinowitch by Martyl Schweig Langsdorf, undated (Box 22, Folder 17)